<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nicolas Angelides</title>
    <description>This is a frontpage to the bubble of Nicolas Angelides. Where it floats, where it has flown and where it will float in the future. Physics, Art and anything in betweeen.
</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 14:52:54 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Dec 2024 14:52:54 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Cygnus</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Cyg_Drawing.png&quot; class=&quot;fit image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt; The above design was commissioned from tattoo artist &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:spaoife1991@gmail.com&quot;&gt; Aoife Tierney&lt;/a&gt; and permanently marks the space over my heart. You can find a picture of the tattoo on my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/regnidorhcs/&quot;&gt;Instagram account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us all remember a warm sunny day from our childhood. Lying careless in a green field, we look up through the canopy of a tree and see the leaves perfectly still in time. The wind is still. As the sun begins to set, we get back on our bike and head back home. During the trip, we can feel a breeze through our hair. The faster we cycle the stronger our hair flutters carelessly in this artificial wind. In this case, even though the air molecules have no effective direction with respect to a stationary observer, they have a distinct relative velocity with respect to a moving observer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blowing this analogy up to the galactic scales, one can replace the air molecules with a cloud of Dark Matter particles, and the bicycle with any vehicle that is in motion with respect to this effectively still cloud. As a result, any such moving object will experience a Dark Matter Wind originating from its relative direction of motion with respect to the stationary galactic plane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us may forget it sometimes, but we are flying through space in the most advanced “self sufficient” space vehicle in the known universe. Our planet is a mobile home, an arc drifting fast through a dark uninhabitable ocean. The direction in which the Earth is moving is defined by two distinct component motions; the Earth’s orbit around the Sun and the Sun’s obit around the galactic centre. By chance alignment, our Galactic orbital direction vector points toward the constellation Cygnus. As a result, an effective wind of Dark Matter particles originates from the direction occupied by Cygnus in the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not claim to be a very focused individual. But when I need a source of inspiration for my research, I close my eyes and imagine that I’m back on that green field. But this time, I can see Cygnus through the canopy of the tree and tell myself that it’s a matter of time until the leaves start blowing in the Dark Matter wind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;  ASTERISM&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cygnus (also known as the Northern Cross) was one of the 48 constellations recorded by the 2nd century astronomer Ptolemy, and represents one of the 88 modern constellations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; Deneb (Arabic dhaneb, meaning “tail,” from the phrase Dhanab ad-Dajājah) – α Cygni (Alpha Cygni)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brightest star in Cygnus and the 19th brightest star on the night sky (60,000 times more luminous the Sun and 20 times heavier), Deneb is a blue-white supergiant located approximately 1,400 light-years away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; Albireo – β Cygni (Beta Cygni)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though Albireo appears to be a single star with the naked eye, it is composed of two distinct component stars. Whether the two stars form a binary (orbiting each other every 100,000 years) or an optical double (being completely unrelated and coincidentally appear as a pair) is not yet known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; Sadr (Arabic ṣadr, meaning “chest”) – γ Cygni (Gamma Cygni)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This yellow-white supergiant star is named for its position in the intersection of the Northern Cross as the chest of Cygnus. Located approximately 1,800 light years away, it is 12 times heavier than the Sun, 150 times larger in radius and emits 33,000 times as much energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; Gienah (Arabic janāħ, meaning “the wing.”) – ε Cygni (Epsilon Cygni)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ginah, located on the right wing of Cygnus is located approximately 73 light-years away is a mere 62 times more luminous than the Sun and 12 times larger in radius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; Rukh (a.k.a. Al al-Fawāris, meaning “the Riders”) – δ Cygni (Delta Cygni)&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stretching over the left wing of Cygnus, Rukh is located approximately 165 light-years away. As the stars move, in around 9,000 years and for a period of 400 years it will replace Polaris as the Earth’s a pole star.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.constellation-guide.com/constellation-list/cygnus-constellation/&quot;&gt; Read more about Cygnus here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/01/11/Cygnus.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/01/11/Cygnus.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vera's voyage</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Vera.png&quot; class=&quot;fit image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;em&gt; The following original story aims to communicate the complex mysteries of the Universe to children of all ages. Feel free to use it for your own outreach endeavors but please do so while respecting my intellectual property rights.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My name is Nicolas and I am a Dark Matter physicist. As a physicist, I get to study the comings and goings of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time thinking about the very large things in the world and the very small things. I think about how the planets move, and I think about how magnets work. I think about how atoms are held together and I think about how stars are arranged in the night sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But none of those is my favourite thing to do. My favourite activity is dreaming. I go to bed at night and dream of worlds filled with crazy characters. I go on adventures that take place on strange planets that I’ve never been on before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During these dreams I enjoy just floating and flying through the stars. I swim through space as if it were the open sea. I travel from planet to planet visiting some of my favourite friends and places. Galaxies are like tropical reefs, rich with life. The space between the Galaxies is dark and often holds many secrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love exploring the emptiness. I look at the distant stars and wonder what the planets that orbit them may look like. I often head out to the unknown and try to find my next adventure. It was on a dream like this that I met a very dear friend of mine; Vera the Dark Matter Space Whale. A night that changed my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a trip just like any other. I had just left our nearest galaxy Andromeda, when suddenly….
I received information regarding pulsation generation in gravitation. A very strange situation for that location. Was this an indication for an unknown civilisation? This needed further examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gravity is the attractive force between all objects heavy or light. It keeps humans on the surface of planets and it keeps moons in orbit. A force so strong it makes stars shine. When an object moves the gravitation around it changes. A pulsation such as this must be coming from a nearby object…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was far from any planet and I could see no lights. I searched, and scanned and looked, but no spacecraft could be found either. All my indicators were indicating and all my detectors detecting. The space in front of me was indeed truly empty. Yet the signal I received seemed stronger by the minute.  How could there be something there if I cannot see it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was music! A piece no human can ever hear or feel, but a piece heard in both space and time. A piece written for the planets themselves. This was incredible! Who could possibly be able to compose and perform a gravitational masterpiece like this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My translator! It was picking up a language in the gravitational pulses! But how could it be? A language as old as the universe itself? This piece was a song!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travelling through the universe all alone.
Travelling through the universe on our own.
With our never ending song, we pull the stars together,
in the vast unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An intelligent creature. How old could it be? What did these words mean? At that point I knew what I had to do. I quickly rerouted the translator to the gravity generator and responded;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travelling through the universe all alone.
Travelling through the universe on my own.
With this beautiful song, I wish to find adventure,
in the vast unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A period of silence followed my song. Silence fitting the emptiness that I was still surrounded by. I began to think the creature was gone forever. Hidden by the emptiness it came from. Thankfully, I was wrong as she responded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Adventurer that I cannot see, I can hear you! My name is Vera and I am very excited to be speaking to you. This is a very VERY rare opportunity. I do not see you as I am made of Dark Matter and you are not. Whales like myself inhabit every corner of this universe, yet we remain unnoticed. There is much to discuss!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spoke for hours. Exchanging information about each other’s hidden worlds. Vera had been travelling for a long time! By the sounds of it, she was there at the very beginning of time! She has been travelling for 13.8 billion years. I am the first creature she has ever come into contact with since her voyage began.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I was raised in a hot and dense universe. A neighbourhood as small as a your fingernail, inhabited by thousands of particles and gases. Everything you can see used to be part of my neighbourhood. The stars, the planets, the entire universe used to be really really small back then. Since everything was so close, things used to be a lot hotter. In fact, hotter than the sun itself. All of my friends were there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Baby protons used to be so positive, born only a second after I was. They used to love playing with the electron and photon households. The photons would always run around, keeping the neighbourhood warm, vibrant and colourful.  They were the fastest of the group. The electrons, even though quite negative, loved bouncing around as much as they did circling the protons. I miss them all so much, even the antisocial and indecisive neutrinos, with their constant character flips.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Unfortunately, I haven’t seen any of them for a long time. As the universe expanded and grew, everybody went their own way and communication stopped. My family, the Dark Matter family, is the largest family of them all. Five times as large as any other family combined. After separating from all the other families we have had one important job; to keep everyone together in the hopes of seeing the other families again!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vera and her family spend their lives singing a song that never ends. Their song binds the galaxies together, allowing life to exist. Without their song, the world as we know it would fly apart. I wondered if any of the particles that make up my body were ever friends with Vera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our conversation, I recognised her frustration. The situation was, in summation, rather unfortunate. Her entire population was in a never ending migration with a single limitation. I had the sensation that I had to help. I had to find a way to help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vera cannot communicate with the rest of the universe, which is why I still cannot see her. Her species, even if five times bigger in size, cannot contact any of their childhood friends. I had to take advantage of this rare opportunity. I had to do it for Vera and her family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On that day I set out on a new adventure. An adventure that I live every day as a physicist. My goal is to help Vera find her friends. I need to remind people of what Vera is and what she does. I need to prove that the entire Dark Matter family exists, and finally shine light in this mysterious world! To create a universe that is once again united.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I have a hard day, I just imagine Vera swimming by, smiling as she knows that it is all a matter of time until she is reunited with her friends.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 15 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/11/15/Vera's-Voyage.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/11/15/Vera's-Voyage.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>If a tree falls in a forest</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Dani.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fit image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project I had the pleasure of collaborating with Information Experience Design graduate &lt;a href=&quot;http://ifatreefalls.rca.ac.uk/daniele-giannetti&quot;&gt;Daniele Giannetti&lt;/a&gt; on an artwork titled “Instance”. The piece was exhibited from 12th of October and until the 4th of November 2018 in Grizedale Forest Visitor’s Centre Project Space. Visit the excibition’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://ifatreefalls.rca.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; to find out more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of “time” has had many interpretations in physics. In special relativity it is interchangeable with space and can be bent and twisted. In nuclear physics it mandates the decay of atoms. Its direction is defined through entropy, framing every single event in a continuous steam. In between each infinitesimally short slice, an infinite universe pulsates. Within each moment secrets are hidden like rare metals coursing through the earth. As artists we capture and represent moments. As scientists we seek them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the search for Dark Matter “time” is a double edged sword. The optimists may claim that it is only a matter of time until Dark Matter is directly observed. With bigger instruments, newer technologies and larger groups of scientist, discovery is just around the corner. The pessimists may claim that depending on the interaction strength the direct detection of Dark Matter may be too rare to ever confirm with certainty. The undecided can only hold their breath and wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some moments are too rare to capture. Some may be too short or too long. Within this framework and during a brainstorm session focusing on using natural elements, the process of erosion was considered. A drop of water may not carry enough force to change a rock, however, millions of drops can carve mountains. Erosion cannot be captured in a single moment. Neither can a single drop be used to predict and describe erosion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This art piece tries to capture the anticipation contained in an instance. Water suspended over a rock, frozen in time and space. We can imagine the water splashing, we can even hear the sound it would make. Dark Matter is an instance away from discovery. An instance that will terraform our view of the universe, shaping our future understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/10/12/If-a-tree-falls-in-a-forest.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/10/12/If-a-tree-falls-in-a-forest.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Observatoire bizarre</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/RA.jpg&quot; class=&quot;fit image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one of the many and confusingly arranged rooms of the Royal Academy of Arts the most extraordinary scientific environment was set. Long pieces of white canvas hanging from the ceiling were swinging a few meters from their allocated projectors. The voices from audience and performers indistinguishable. The expertise, undeniable. The subject, bizarre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself overwhelmed by anxiety in a room full of alcohol, strangers and colleagues. The creased lab-coat that I was given allowed me to blend right in to my surroundings, however, my aimless pace persisted.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2018/02/17/Observatoire-Bizarre.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2018/02/17/Observatoire-Bizarre.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
